<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="AiW">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="statement">ALICE'S ADVENTURES IN WONDERLAND</title>
		    <title type="distinctive">THE <quote>STORYLAND</quote> SERIES</title>
                <author>Carroll, Lewis, 1832-1898.</author>
                <respStmt xml:id="PGB">
                    <orgName ref="https://www.gutenberg.org/">The Project Gutenberg</orgName>
                    <resp>electronic edition</resp>
                </respStmt>
		<respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic edition edited by:</resp>
                    <name>Jason Isbell, </name>
                    <name>Irma Spehar.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date when="1916">1916</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>
                    <orgName ref="https://www.gutenberg.org/about/">The Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation</orgName>
                </authority>
                <date when="2006-08-12">August 12, 2006</date>                 
                <availability>
                    <p> Available for reuse, according to the terms of the <ref target="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/19033/19033-h/19033-h.htm">Project Gutenberg License</ref>.</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="url">https://www.gutenberg.org/files/19033/19033-h/19033-h.htm</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Carroll, Lewis, 1832-1898.</author>
                    <title type="statement">ALICE'S ADVENTURES IN WONDERLAND</title>
                    
			<title type="distinctive">THE <quote>STORYLAND</quote> SERIES</title>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Alice">
                        <persName type="person">
                            <forename>Alice</forename>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-White-Rabbit">
                        <persName type="animal">White Rabbit</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Mouse">
                        <persName type="animal">Mouse</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Duck">
                        <persName type="animal">Duck</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Dodo">
                        <persName type="animal">Dodo</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Lory">
                        <persName type="animal">Lory</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Eaglet">
                        <persName type="animal">Eaglet</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Caterpillar">
                        <persName type="animal">Caterpillar</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Pigeon">
                        <persName type="animal">Pigeon</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="AiW-Duchess">
                        <persName type="person">Duchess</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="prose" xml:id="AiWCharacterAnalysis">
        <body>
		<div1 type="chapter" n="1">
		<head>DOWN RGE RABBIT HOLE</head>
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> was beginning to get very tired of sitting by her sister on the bank, and of having nothing to do. Once or twice she had peeped into the book her sister was reading, but it had no pictures or conversations in it, <quote>and what is the use of a book,</quote> thought Alice, <quote>without pictures or conversations?</quote></p>
                
                <p>So she was considering in her own mind (as well as she could, for the day made her feel very sleepy and stupid), whether the pleasure of making a daisy-chain would be worth the trouble of getting up and picking the daisies, when suddenly a <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">White Rabbit</name> with pink eyes ran close by her.</p>
             
                <p>There was nothing so very remarkable in that, nor did <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> think it so very much out of the way to hear the Rabbit say to itself, "Oh dear! Oh dear! I shall be too late!" But when the Rabbit actually took a watch out of its waistcoat-pocket and looked at it and then hurried on, <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> started to her feet, for it flashed across her mind that she had never before seen a rabbit with either a waistcoat-pocket, or a watch to take out of it, and, burning with curiosity, she ran across the field after it and was just in time to see it pop down a large rabbit-hole, under the hedge. In another moment, down went <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> after it!</p>
                
                <pb n="4"/>
                
                <p>The rabbit-hole went straight on like a tunnel for some way and then dipped suddenly down, so suddenly that <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> had not a moment to think about stopping herself before she found herself falling down what seemed to be a very deep well.</p>
                
                <p>Either the well was very deep, or she fell very slowly, for she had plenty of time, as she went down, to look about her. First, she tried to make out what she was coming to, but it was too dark to see anything; then she looked at the sides of the well and noticed that they were filled with cupboards and book-shelves; here and there she saw maps and pictures hung upon pegs. She took down a jar from one of the shelves as she passed. It was labeled <quote>ORANGE MARMALADE,</quote> but, to her great disappointment, it was empty; she did not like to drop the jar, so managed to put it into one of the cupboards as she fell past it.</p>
                <pb n="5"/>
                <p>Down, down, down! Would the fall never come to an end? There was nothing else to do, so <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> soon began talking to herself. <quote>Dinah'll miss me very much to-night, I should think!</quote> (Dinah was the cat.) <quote>I hope they'll remember her saucer of milk at tea-time. Dinah, my dear, I wish you were down here with me!</quote> <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> felt that she was dozing off, when suddenly, thump! thump! down she came upon a heap of sticks and dry leaves, and the fall was over.</p>
                
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> was not a bit hurt, and she jumped up in a moment. She looked up, but it was all dark overhead; before her was another long passage and the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">White Rabbit</name> was still in sight, hurrying down it. There was not a moment to be lost. Away went <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> like the wind and was just in time to hear it say, as it turned a corner, <quote>Oh, my ears and whiskers, how late it's getting!</quote> She was close behind it when she turned the corner, but the Rabbit was no longer to be seen.</p>
                
                <p>She found herself in a long, low hall, which was lit up by a row of lamps hanging from the roof. There were doors all 'round the hall, but they were all locked; and when <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> had been all the way down one side and up the other, trying every door, she walked sadly down the middle, wondering how she was ever to get out again.</p>
                
                <pb n="6" facs="https://iiif.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/iiif/image/63ed8572-9086-4dac-ba08-5a9cf1446704"/>
                
                <p>Suddenly she came upon a little table, all made of solid glass. There was nothing on it but a tiny golden key, and Alice's first idea was that this might belong to one of the doors of the hall; but, alas! either the locks were too large, or the key was too small, but, at any rate, it would not open any of them. However, on the second time 'round, she came upon a low curtain she had not noticed before, and behind it was a little door about fifteen inches high. She tried the little golden key in the lock, and to her great delight, it fitted!</p>
                
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> opened the door and found that it led into a small passage, not much larger than a rat-hole; she knelt down and looked along the passage into the loveliest garden you ever saw. How she longed to get out of that dark hall and wander about among those beds of bright flowers and those cool fountains, but she could not even get her head through the doorway. <quote>Oh,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, <quote>how I wish I could shut up like a telescope! I think I could, if I only knew how to begin.</quote></p>
                
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> went back to the table, half hoping she might find another key on it, or at any rate, a book of rules for shutting people up like telescopes. This time she found a little bottle on it (<quote>which certainly was not here before,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>), and tied 'round the neck of the bottle was a paper label, with the words <quote>DRINK ME</quote> beautifully printed on it in large letters.</p>
                
                <pb n="7"/>
                
                <p><quote>No, I'll look first,</quote> she said, <quote>and see whether it's marked 'poison' or not,</quote> for she had never forgotten that, if you drink from a bottle marked <quote>poison,</quote> it is almost certain to disagree with you, sooner or later. However, this bottle was not marked <quote>poison,</quote> so <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> ventured to taste it, and, finding it very nice (it had a sort of mixed flavor of cherry-tart, custard, pineapple, roast turkey, toffy and hot buttered toast), she very soon finished it off.</p>
                
                <p><quote>What a curious feeling!</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>. <quote>I must be shutting up like a telescope!</quote></p>
                
                <p>And so it was indeed! She was now only ten inches high, and her face brightened up at the thought that she was now the right size for going through the little door into that lovely garden.</p>
                
                <p>After awhile, finding that nothing more happened, she decided on going into the garden at once; but, alas for poor <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>! When she got to the door, she found she had forgotten the little golden key, and when she went back to the table for it, she found she could not possibly reach it: she could see it quite plainly through the glass and she tried her best to climb up one of the legs of the table, but it was too slippery, and when she had tired herself out with trying, the poor little thing sat down and cried.</p>
                
                <p><quote>Come, there's no use in crying like that!</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> to herself rather sharply. <quote>I advise you to leave off this minute!</quote> She generally gave herself very good advice (though she very seldom followed it), and sometimes she scolded herself so severely as to bring tears into her eyes.</p>
                
                <pb n="8"/>
                
                <p>Soon her eye fell on a little glass box that was lying under the table: she opened it and found in it a very small cake, on which the words <quote>EAT ME</quote> were beautifully marked in currants. <quote>Well, I'll eat it,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, <quote>and if it makes me grow larger, I can reach the key; and if it makes me grow smaller, I can creep under the door: so either way I'll get into the garden, and I don't care which happens!</quote></p>
                
                <p>She ate a little bit and said anxiously to herself, <quote>Which way? Which way?</quote> holding her hand on the top of her head to feel which way she was growing; and she was quite surprised to find that she remained the same size. So she set to work and very soon finished off the cake.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="chapter" n="2">
                <head>THE POOL OF TEARS</head>
                <p><quote>Curiouser and curiouser!</quote> cried <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> (she was so much surprised that for the moment she quite forgot how to speak good English). <quote>Now I'm opening out like the largest telescope that ever was! Good-by, feet! Oh, my poor little feet, I wonder who will put on your shoes and stockings for you now, dears? I shall be a great deal too far off to trouble myself about you.</quote></p>
                <p>Just at this moment her head struck against the roof of the hall; in fact, she was now rather more than nine feet high, and she at once took up the little golden key and hurried off to the garden door.</p>
                <p>Poor <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>! It was as much as she could do, lying down on one side, to look through into the garden with one eye; but to get through was more hopeless than ever. She sat down and began to cry again.</p>
                <p>She went on shedding gallons of tears, until there was a large pool all 'round her and reaching half down the hall.</p>
                <p>After a time, she heard a little pattering of feet in the distance and she hastily dried her eyes to see what was coming. It was the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">White Rabbit</name> returning, splendidly dressed, with a pair of white kid-gloves in one hand and a large fan in the other. He came trotting along in a great hurry, muttering to himself, <quote>Oh! the <name ref="#AiW-Duchess" type="person">Duchess</name>, the <name ref="#AiW-Duchess" type="person">Duchess</name>! Oh! <emph>won't</emph> she be savage if I've kept her waiting!</quote></p>
                <pb n="9"/>
                <p>When the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name> came near her, <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> began, in a low, timid voice, <quote>If you please, sir—</quote> The <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name> started violently, dropped the white kid-gloves and the fan and skurried away into the darkness as hard as he could go.</p>
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> took up the fan and gloves and she kept fanning herself all the time she went on talking. <quote>Dear, dear! How queer everything is to-day! And yesterday things went on just as usual. <emph>Was</emph> I the same when I got up this morning? But if I'm not the same, the next question is, 'Who in the world am I?' Ah, <emph>that's</emph> the great puzzle!</quote></p>
                <p>As she said this, she looked down at her hands and was surprised to see that she had put on one of the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit's</name> little white kid-gloves while she was talking. <quote>How <emph>can</emph> I have done that?</quote> she thought. <quote>I must be growing small again.</quote> She got up and went to the table to measure herself by it and found that she was now about two feet high and was going on shrinking rapidly. She soon found out that the cause of this was the fan she was holding and she dropped it hastily, just in time to save herself from shrinking away altogether.</p>
                <pb n="10"/>
                <p><quote>That <emph>was</emph> a narrow escape!</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, a good deal frightened at the sudden change, but very glad to find herself still in existence. <quote>And now for the garden!</quote> And she ran with all speed back to the little door; but, alas! the little door was shut again and the little golden key was lying on the glass table as before. <quote>Things are worse than ever,</quote> thought the poor child, <quote>for I never was so small as this before, never!</quote></p>
                <p>As she said these words, her foot slipped, and in another moment, splash! she was up to her chin in salt-water. Her first idea was that she had somehow fallen into the sea. However, she soon made out that she was in the pool of tears which she had wept when she was nine feet high.</p>
                <p>Just then she heard something splashing about in the pool a little way off, and she swam nearer to see what it was: she soon made out that it was only a mouse that had slipped in like herself.</p>
                <pb n="11"/>
                <p><quote>Would it be of any use, now,</quote> thought <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, <quote>to speak to this mouse? Everything is so out-of-the-way down here that I should think very likely it can talk; at any rate, there's no harm in trying.</quote> So she began, <quote>O <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name>, do you know the way out of this pool? I am very tired of swimming about here, O <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name>!</quote> The <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name> looked at her rather inquisitively and seemed to her to wink with one of its little eyes, but it said nothing.</p>
                <p><quote>Perhaps it doesn't understand English,</quote> thought <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>. <quote>I dare say it's a French mouse, come over with William the Conqueror.</quote> So she began again: <quote>Où est ma chatte?</quote> which was the first sentence in her French lesson-book. The <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name> gave a sudden leap out of the water and seemed to quiver all over with fright. <quote>Oh, I beg your pardon!</quote> cried <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> hastily, afraid that she had hurt the poor animal's feelings. <quote>I quite forgot you didn't like cats.</quote></p>
                <p><quote>Not like cats!</quote> cried the <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name> in a shrill, passionate voice. <quote>Would <emph>you</emph> like cats, if you were me?</quote></p>
                <p><quote>Well, perhaps not,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> in a soothing tone; <quote>don't be angry about it. And yet I wish I could show you our cat Dinah. I think you'd take a fancy to cats, if you could only see her. She is such a dear, quiet thing.</quote> The <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name> was bristling all over and she felt certain it must be really offended. <quote>We won't talk about her any more, if you'd rather not.</quote></p>
                <p><quote>We, indeed!</quote> cried the <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name>, who was trembling down to the end of its tail. <quote>As if I would talk on such a subject! Our family always <emph>hated</emph> cats—nasty, low, vulgar things! Don't let me hear the name again!</quote></p>
                <pb n="12" facs="https://iiif.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/iiif/image/333dbc25-9ef8-4654-8cc0-e5c88a4fb758"/>
                <p><quote>I won't indeed!</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, in a great hurry to change the subject of conversation. <quote>Are you—are you fond—of—of dogs? There is such a nice little dog near our house, I should like to show you! It kills all the rats and—oh, dear!</quote> cried Alice in a sorrowful tone. <quote>I'm afraid I've offended it again!</quote> For the <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name> was swimming away from her as hard as it could go, and making quite a commotion in the pool as it went.</p>
                <p>So she called softly after it, <quote><name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name> dear! Do come back again, and we won't talk about cats, or dogs either, if you don't like them!</quote> When the <name ref="#AiW-Mouse" type="animal">Mouse</name> heard this, it turned 'round and swam slowly back to her; its face was quite pale, and it said, in a low, trembling voice, <quote>Let us get to the shore and then I'll tell you my history and you'll understand why it is I hate cats and dogs.</quote></p>
                <p>It was high time to go, for the pool was getting quite crowded with the birds and animals that had fallen into it; there were a <name ref="#AiWDuck" type="animal">Duck</name> and a <name ref="#AiWDodo" type="animal">Dodo</name>, a <name ref="#AiWLory" type="animal">Lory</name> and an <name ref="#AiWEaglet" type="animal">Eaglet</name>, and several other curious creatures. <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> led the way and the whole party swam to the shore.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="chapter" n="4" >
                <head>THE RABBIT SENDS IN A LITTLE BILL</head>
                <p>It was the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name>, trotting slowly back again and looking anxiously about as it went, as if it had lost something; Alice heard it muttering to itself, <quote>The <name ref="#AiW-Duchess" type="person">Duchess</name>! The <name ref="#AiW-Duchess" type="person">Duchess</name>! Oh, my dear paws! Oh, my fur and whiskers! She'll get me executed, as sure as ferrets are ferrets! Where <emph>can</emph> I have dropped them, I wonder?</quote> <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> guessed in a moment that it was looking for the fan and the pair of white kid-gloves and she very good-naturedly began hunting about for them, but they were nowhere to be seen—everything seemed to have changed since her swim in the pool, and the great hall, with the glass table and the little door, had vanished completely.</p> 
		    <pb n="21"/>
                <p>Very soon the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name> noticed <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, and called to her, in an angry tone, <quote>Why, Mary Ann, what <emph>are</emph> you doing out here? Run home this moment and fetch me a pair of gloves and a fan! Quick, now!</quote> </p>
                <p> <quote>He took me for his housemaid!</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, as she ran off. <quote>How surprised he'll be when he finds out who I am!</quote> As she said this, she came upon a neat little house, on the door of which was a bright brass plate with the name <quote>W. RABBIT</quote> engraved upon it. She went in without knocking and hurried upstairs, in great fear lest she should meet the real Mary Ann and be turned out of the house before she had found the fan and gloves. </p>
                <p>By this time, <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> had found her way into a tidy little room with a table in the window, and on it a fan and two or three pairs of tiny white kid-gloves; she took up the fan and a pair of the gloves and was just going to leave the room, when her eyes fell upon a little bottle that stood near the looking-glass. She uncorked it and put it to her lips, saying to herself, <quote>I do hope it'll make me grow large again, for, really, I'm quite tired of being such a tiny little thing!</quote></p>
                <p>Before she had drunk half the bottle, she found her head pressing against the ceiling, and had to stoop to save her neck from being broken. She hastily put down the bottle, remarking, <quote>That's quite enough—I hope I sha'n't grow any more.</quote> </p>
                <p>Alas! It was too late to wish that! She went on growing and growing and very soon she had to kneel down on the floor. Still she went on growing, and, as a last resource, she put one arm out of the window and one foot up the chimney, and said to herself, <quote>Now I can do no more, whatever happens. What <emph>will</emph> become of me?</quote> </p> 
		    <pb n="22" facs="https://iiif.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/iiif/image/333dbc25-9ef8-4654-8cc0-e5c88a4fb758"/>
                <p>Luckily for <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, the little magic bottle had now had its full effect and she grew no larger. After a few minutes she heard a voice outside and stopped to listen. </p>
                <p><quote>Mary Ann! Mary Ann!</quote> said the voice. <quote>Fetch me my gloves this moment!</quote> Then came a little pattering of feet on the stairs. <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> knew it was the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name> coming to look for her and she trembled till she shook the house, quite forgetting that she was now about a thousand times as large as the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name> and had no reason to be afraid of it. </p>
                <p>Presently the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name> came up to the door and tried to open it; but as the door opened inwards and <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>'s elbow was pressed hard against it, that attempt proved a failure. <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> heard it say to itself, <quote>Then I'll go 'round and get in at the window.</quote> </p>
                <p><said><emph>That</emph> you won't!</said> thought <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>; and after waiting till she fancied she heard the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name> just under the window, she suddenly spread out her hand and made a snatch in the air. She did not get hold of anything, but she heard a little shriek and a fall and a crash of broken glass, from which she concluded that it was just possible it had fallen into a cucumber-frame or something of that sort.</p>
		    <pb n="23"/>
                <p>Next came an angry voice—the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name>'s—<quote>Pat! Pat! Where are you?</quote> And then a voice she had never heard before, <quote>Sure then, I'm here! Digging for apples, yer honor!</quote></p>
                <p><quote>Here! Come and help me out of this! Now tell me, Pat, what's that in the window?</quote></p>
                <p><quote>Sure, it's an arm, yer honor!</quote></p>
                <p><quote>Well, it's got no business there, at any rate; go and take it away!</quote></p>
                <p>There was a long silence after this and <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> could only hear whispers now and then, and at last she spread out her hand again and made another snatch in the air. This time there were <emph>two</emph> little shrieks and more sounds of broken glass. <quote>I wonder what they'll do next!</quote> thought <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>. <quote>As for pulling me out of the window, I only wish they <emph>could!</emph></quote></p>
                <p>She waited for some time without hearing anything more. At last came a rumbling of little cart-wheels and the sound of a good many voices all talking together. She made out the words: <quote>Where's the other ladder? Bill's got the other—Bill! Here, Bill! Will the roof bear?—Who's to go down the chimney?—Nay, <emph>I</emph> sha'n't! <emph>You</emph> do it! Here, Bill! The master says you've got to go down the chimney!</quote></p>
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> drew her foot as far down the chimney as she could and waited till she heard a little animal scratching and scrambling about in the chimney close above her; then she gave one sharp kick and waited to see what would happen next.</p>
                <pb n="24"/>
		    <p>The first thing she heard was a general chorus of <quote>There goes Bill!</quote> then the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name>'s voice alone—<quote>Catch him, you by the hedge!</quote> Then silence and then another confusion of voices—<quote>Hold up his head—Brandy now—Don't choke him—What happened to you?</quote></p>
                <p>Last came a little feeble, squeaking voice, <quote>Well, I hardly know—No more, thank ye. I'm better now—all I know is, something comes at me like a Jack-in-the-box and up I goes like a sky-rocket!</quote></p>
                <p>After a minute or two of silence, they began moving about again, and <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> heard the <name ref="#AiW-White-Rabbit" type="animal">Rabbit</name> say, <quote>A barrowful will do, to begin with.</quote></p>
                <p><quote>A barrowful of <emph>what</emph>?</quote> thought <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>. But she had not long to doubt, for the next moment a shower of little pebbles came rattling in at the window and some of them hit her in the face. <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> noticed, with some surprise, that the pebbles were all turning into little cakes as they lay on the floor and a bright idea came into her head. <quote>If I eat one of these cakes,</quote> she thought, <quote>it's sure to make <emph>some</emph> change in my size.</quote></p>
                <p>So she swallowed one of the cakes and was delighted to find that she began shrinking directly. As soon as she was small enough to get through the door, she ran out of the house and found quite a crowd of little animals and birds waiting outside. They all made a rush at <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> the moment she appeared, but she ran off as hard as she could and soon found herself safe in a thick wood.</p>
                <p>The <name ref="#AiW-Duchess" type="person">Duchess</name> tucked her arm affectionately into <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>'s.</p>
                <p><quote>The first thing I've got to do,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> to herself, as she wandered about in the wood, <quote>is to grow to my right size again; and the second thing is to find my way into that lovely garden. I suppose I ought to eat or drink something or other, but the great question is 'What?'</quote></p>
		    <pb n="25"/>
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> looked all around her at the flowers and the blades of grass, but she could not see anything that looked like the right thing to eat or drink under the circumstances. There was a large mushroom growing near her, about the same height as herself. She stretched herself up on tiptoe and peeped over the edge and her eyes immediately met those of a large blue caterpillar, that was sitting on the top, with its arms folded, quietly smoking a long hookah and taking not the smallest notice of her or of anything else.</p> 
		    <pb n="26"/>
		  
            </div1> 
		
            <div1 type="chapter" n="5"> 
                <head>ADVICE FROM A CATERPILLAR</head>
                <p>At last the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name> took the hookah out of its mouth and addressed <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> in a languid, sleepy voice.</p>
                <p><quote>Who are <emph>you</emph> ?</quote>said the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name>.</p>
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> replied, rather shyly, <quote>I—I hardly know, sir, just at present—at least I know who I was when I got up this morning, but I think I must have changed several times since then.</quote></p>
                <p><quote>What do you mean by that?</quote> said the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name>, sternly. <quote>Explain yourself!</quote></p> <pb facs="https://iiif.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/iiif/image/3aff8c83-7dfb-4d6c-b15a-c2b40771c57c/info.json"/>
                <p><quote>I can't explain <emph>myself</emph>, I'm afraid, sir,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, <quote> because I'm not myself, you see—being so many different sizes in a day is very confusing.</quote> She drew herself up and said very gravely, <quote>I think you ought to tell me who <emph>you</emph> are, first.</quote></p>
                <p><quote>Why?</quote> said the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name>.</p>
                <p>As <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> could not think of any good reason and the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name> seemed to be in a <emph>very</emph> unpleasant state of mind, she turned away.</p>
                <p><quote>Come back!</quote> the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name> called after her. <quote>I've something important to say!</quote> <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> turned and came back again.</p>
                <p><quote>Keep your temper</quote>, said the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name>.</p>
		    <pb n="27"/>
                <p><quote>Is that all?</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, swallowing down her anger as well as she could.</p>
                <p><quote>No</quote>, said the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name>.</p>
                <p>It unfolded its arms, took the hookah out of its mouth again, and said, <quote>So you think you're changed, do you?</quote></p>
                <p><quote>I'm afraid, I am, sir,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>. <quote>I can't remember things as I used—and I don't keep the same size for ten minutes together!</quote></p>
                <p><quote>What size do you want to be?</quote> asked the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name>.</p>
                <p><quote>Oh, I'm not particular as to size,</quote> <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> hastily replied, <quote>only one doesn't like changing so often, you know. I should like to be a <emph>little</emph> larger, sir, if you wouldn't mind,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>. <quote>Three inches is such a wretched height to be.</quote></p>
                <p><quote>It is a very good height indeed!</quote> said the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name> angrily, rearing itself upright as it spoke (it was exactly three inches high).</p> 
		    <pb n="28"/>
                <p>In a minute or two, the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name> got down off the mushroom and crawled away into the grass, merely remarking, as it went, <quote>One side will make you grow taller, and the other side will make you grow shorter.</quote></p>
                <p><quote>One side of <emph>what</emph>? The other side of <emph>what</emph>?</quote> thought <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> to herself.</p>
                <p><quote>Of the mushroom,</quote> said the <name ref="#AiW-Caterpillar" type="animal">Caterpillar</name>, just as if she had asked it aloud; and in another moment, it was out of sight.</p>
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> remained looking thoughtfully at the mushroom for a minute, trying to make out which were the two sides of it. At last she stretched her arms 'round it as far as they would go, and broke off a bit of the edge with each hand.</p>
                <p><quote>And now which is which?</quote> she said to herself, and nibbled a little of the right-hand bit to try the effect. The next moment she felt a violent blow underneath her chin—it had struck her foot!</p>
                <p>She was a good deal frightened by this very sudden change, as she was shrinking rapidly; so she set to work at once to eat some of the other bit. Her chin was pressed so closely against her foot that there was hardly room to open her mouth; but she did it at last and managed to swallow a morsel of the left-hand bit....</p>
                <p><quote>Come, my head's free at last!</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>; but all she could see, when she looked down, was an immense length of neck, which seemed to rise like a stalk out of a sea of green leaves that lay far below her.</p>
                <p><quote>Where <emph>have</emph> my shoulders got to? And oh, my poor hands, how is it I can't see you?</quote> She was delighted to find that her neck would bend about easily in any direction, like a serpent. She had just succeeded in curving it down into a graceful zigzag and was going to dive in among the leaves, when a sharp hiss made her draw back in a hurry—a large pigeon had flown into her face and was beating her violently with its wings.</p>
                <p><quote>Serpent!</quote> cried the <name ref="#AiW-Pigeon" type="animal">Pigeon</name>.</p>
		    <pb n="29"/>
                <p><quote>I'm <emph>not</emph> a serpent!</quote>I said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> indignantly. <quote>Let me alone!</quote></p>
                <p><quote>I've tried the roots of trees, and I've tried banks, and I've tried hedges,</quote> the <name ref="#AiW-Pigeon" type="animal">Pigeon</name> went on, <quote>but those serpents! There's no pleasing them!</quote></p>
                <p><name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> was more and more puzzled.</p>
                <p><quote>As if it wasn't trouble enough hatching the eggs,</quote> said the <name ref="#AiW-Pigeon" type="animal">Pigeon</name>, <quote>but I must be on the look-out for serpents, night and day! And just as I'd taken the highest tree in the wood,</quote> continued the <name ref="#AiW-Pigeon" type="animal">Pigeon</name>, raising its voice to a shriek, <quote>and just as I was thinking I should be free of them at last, they must needs come wriggling down from the sky! Ugh, Serpent!</quote></p>
                <p><quote>But I'm <emph>not</emph> a serpent, I tell you!</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>. <quote>I'm a—I'm a—I'm a little girl,</quote> she added rather doubtfully, as she remembered the number of <pb/>changes she had gone through that day.</p>
		    <pb n="30"/>
                <p><quote>You're looking for eggs, I know <emph>that</emph> well enough,</quote> said the <name ref="#AiW-Pigeon" type="animal">Pigeon</name>; <quote>and what does it matter to me whether you're a little girl or a serpent?</quote></p>
                <p><quote>It matters a good deal to <emph>me</emph>,</quote> said <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> hastily; <quote>but I'm not looking for eggs, as it happens, and if I was, I shouldn't want <emph>yours</emph>—I don't like them raw.</quote></p>
                <p><quote>Well, be off, then!</quote> said the <name ref="#AiW-Pigeon" type="animal">Pigeon</name> in a sulky tone, as it settled down again into its nest. <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name> crouched down among the trees as well as she could, for her neck kept getting entangled among the branches, and every now and then she had to stop and untwist it. After awhile she remembered that she still held the pieces of mushroom in her hands, and she set to work very carefully, nibbling first at one and then at the other, and growing sometimes taller and sometimes shorter, until she had succeeded in bringing herself down to her usual height.</p>
                <p>It was so long since she had been anything near the right size that it felt quite strange at first. <quote>The next thing is to get into that beautiful garden—how is that to be done, I wonder?</quote> As she said this, she came suddenly upon an open place, with a little house in it about four feet high. <quote>Whoever lives there,</quote> thought <name ref="#AiW-Alice" type="person">Alice</name>, <quote>it'll never do to come upon them <emph>this</emph> size; why, I should frighten them out of their wits!</quote> She did not venture to go near the house till she had brought herself down to nine inches high.</p>
		    <pb n="31" facs="https://iiif.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/iiif/image/3aff8c83-7dfb-4d6c-b15a-c2b40771c57c"/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
